<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-09-05T18:50:55+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Daidarai</title><subtitle>having fun and researching some topics</subtitle><author><name>me</name></author><entry><title type="html">Brief: Explore The Ghent Altarpiece by Van Eyck</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ghent-altarpiece" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Brief: Explore The Ghent Altarpiece by Van Eyck" /><published>2024-08-29T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-08-29T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Ghent-Altarpiece-web</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ghent-altarpiece"><![CDATA[<p>Beautiful piece of art, right?</p>

<p>You can see before restoration, during and after restoration versions of the Ghent Altarpiece on <a href="https://closertovaneyck.kikirpa.be/">this website</a>. There is also option to close or open the altar.</p>

<p>Aside from Ghent Altarpiece, it is also called Adoration of the Mystic Lamb.</p>

<figure style="float:center; margin:10px 10px;">
  <img src="assets\img\ghent-altarpiece.png" width="450" height="400" />
  <figcaption style="font-style: italic; font-size: 13px; text-align: center; margin-top: 5px;"> After restoration<br />Author: Van Eyck</figcaption>
</figure>

<figure style="float:center; margin:10px 10px;">
  <img src="assets\img\ghent-altarpiece-before.png" width="450" height="400" />
  <figcaption style="font-style: italic; font-size: 13px; text-align: center; margin-top: 5px;"> Before restoration<br />Author: Van Eyck</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>It was painted by brothers Hubert and Jan van Eyck in Belgium. They began painting the altarpiece around mid-1420s and completed the work in 1432. There was also text found onthe frame of the central panel, it says: “Hubert van Eyck, the greatest painter ever, started this work; his brother Jan, who came second in painting, completed this arduous task at the request of Joos Vijd. He entrusts this work to you on 6 May 1432. Admire what they have accomplished,” according to Saint Bavo’s Cathedral’s website. But Art historians coudln’t figure out which panel painted which brother.</p>

<p>This artpiece experienced quite a backlash from the public, but the restoration was actually accurate. Van Eyck really did draw the lamb like this, the lamb was overpainted in 16th century so it would look more like a lamb. So, Van Eyck was going for that humanoid look and now it is back.</p>

<p>Some work is not restored yet, but we can see before restoration  version of some panels, for example panels with Adam and Eva.</p>

<figure style="float:center; margin:10px 10px;">
  <img src="assets\img\eva-altar.png" width="180" height="570" />
  <figcaption style="font-style: italic; font-size: 13px; text-align: center; margin-top: 5px;"> Eva <br />Author: Van Eyck</figcaption>
</figure>

<figure style="float:center; margin:10px 10px;">
  <img src="assets\img\adam-altar.png" width="180" height="570" />
  <figcaption style="font-style: italic; font-size: 13px; text-align: center; margin-top: 5px;"> Adam <br />Author: Van Eyck</figcaption>
</figure>

<h3 id="references">References:</h3>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>The Ghent Altarpiece Restored. Closer to Van Eyck. <a href="https://closertovaneyck.kikirpa.be/ghentaltarpiece/#home">Link here.</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>History. The Ghent Altarpiece. <a href="https://www.sintbaafskathedraal.be/en/history/the-ghent-altarpiece/">Link here.</a></p>
  </li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Daidarai</name></author><category term="brief" /><category term="brief" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Beautiful piece of art, right?]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/altar.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/altar.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Brief: Mappa Mundi, the Largest Medieval Map</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/mappamundi" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Brief: Mappa Mundi, the Largest Medieval Map" /><published>2024-08-27T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-08-27T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Mappa-mundi</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/mappamundi"><![CDATA[<p>I came across an online medieval map from 1300. You can explore this map of inhabited part of the world (roughly equivalent to Europe, Asia and North Africa) yourself on <a href="https://www.themappamundi.co.uk/">its website</a>. Aside from mythical races (for example Sciapods, race of people with one huge foot, which they used as an umbrella), that are drawn on this map, there are also beasts, legends and biblical stories displayed. Yes, it is not really literal depiction of the world. Especially with that unicorn and other stuff going on there.</p>]]></content><author><name>Daidarai</name></author><category term="brief" /><category term="brief" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I came across an online medieval map from 1300. You can explore this map of inhabited part of the world (roughly equivalent to Europe, Asia and North Africa) yourself on its website. Aside from mythical races (for example Sciapods, race of people with one huge foot, which they used as an umbrella), that are drawn on this map, there are also beasts, legends and biblical stories displayed. Yes, it is not really literal depiction of the world. Especially with that unicorn and other stuff going on there.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/mappamundi.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/mappamundi.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">This Devil Was Too Beautiful: The Satan statues by Geefs’ brothers</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/the-satan-statue-geefs" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="This Devil Was Too Beautiful: The Satan statues by Geefs’ brothers" /><published>2024-08-22T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-08-22T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Geefs</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/the-satan-statue-geefs"><![CDATA[<p>The year is 1837 and the Belgian church just commissioned a devil sculpture for St. Paul’s Cathedral in Liége. The devil statue was meant to be part of an even bigger project — the new pulpit with theme “the Triumph of Religion over the Genius of Evil”. 
The sculptor Guillaume Geefs was put in charge of designing the pulpit. The creation of the devil sculpture was entrusted to Guillaume’s younger brother – Joseph Geefs. (…) And Joseph created one of the <strong>“most disturbing works of the period”</strong>  – the Genius of Evil.</p>

<figure style="float:center; margin:10px 10px;">
  <img src="assets/img/cathedral-mid-19th.jpg" width="550" height="350" />
  <figcaption style="font-style: italic; font-size: 13px; text-align: center; margin-top: 5px;"> St. Paul Cathedral in Liége<br />Author: Joseph Fussell (1818-1912)</figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="i-reaction-of-that-time-1840-1844">I. Reaction of that time (1840-1844)</h2>

<figure style="float:right;margin:10px 10px">
  <img src="assets/img/joseph-g-stat.jpg" alt="Caption Text" width="250" height="500" />
  <figcaption style="font-style: italic; font-size: 13px; margin-top: 5px;">Joseph Geefs' statue, also called <br /> L'ange du mal.<br /> Source: Georges Jansoone (JoJan), wiki</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Joseph’s statue, The Genius of Evil, originally known as Le génie du mal*, was installed in the Cathedral in 1844 as part of the new pulpit. But before that the statue had been displayed for public and was commented on by newspapers and art critics of that time.</p>

<p>In 1840 the work was being described as “an admirable statue” by a Belgian art critic Félix Stappaerts and as „one of the best in the exhibition“ in The Renaissance Chronicle of Art and Literature.
In 1842, Revue Belge mentioned that, out of six Joseph’s sculptures that were exhibited, <strong>“the Genius of Evil seems worthy of attention.”</strong></p>

<p>In L’Indépendance Belge published in 1843 it was said that the sculpture <strong>“adorned the last exhibition in Brussels”</strong> and <strong>“placed him at the forefront of statuaries of that time”.</strong></p>

<p>In the same year the statue was praised also in a book titled Fine arts exhibition in The Hague, quote, “The Genius of Evil has a remarkable expression (…) It is both simple and poetic, and the drawing exhibits great nobility. (…) The forms leave nothing to be desired in terms of elegance and beauty.”</p>

<p>Then, once again in The Renaissance Chronicle of Art and Literature is mentioned that “as for the modeling, it is skillful and well-studied, and the execution is remarkably energetic.”</p>

<figure style="float:right;margin:10px 10px;">
  <img src="assets/img/joseph-geefs-back.jpg" alt="Caption Text" width="260" height="480" />
  <figcaption style="font-style: italic; font-size: 13px; margin-top: 5px;"> The back of Joseph Geefs' statue;<br />Source: John Bedell, 2014</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>So, it is clear that art critics praised Joseph’s statue. In terms of Christianity the sculpture was commented on also quite positively. L‘Indépendence Belge wrote: “The statue of the Genius of Evil is already known: it is placed at the entrance and at the foot of the pulpit <strong>symbolizing Satan’s despair</strong>, crushed under the edifice of Faith that frees humanity from his disastrous empire. The priest confronts evil directly as he ascends the steps of the mystical mountain placed between heaven and earth, from which must spring the word of consolation.”</p>

<p>The mystical mountain actually represents the pulpit itself, as the devil was placed under the stairs of the pulpit in the center, on the pedestal. The priest was confronting the devil while going up the stairs. Due to the statue’s positioning, the devil is turning his back on the statues of saints at the front of the pulpit, which is another subtle metaphorical detail.</p>

<p>In summary, the statue had been receiving praise since 1840. However, in 1844, the devil statue was installed in St. Paul’s Cathedral, only to be swiftly <strong>removed</strong> by the church.</p>

<h2 id="ii-removed-by-the-church">II. Removed by the church</h2>
<p>Even though  the Devil statue “aroused lively and profound admiration” and was even popular among high society, the church didn’t like it that much (and when I say “the church”, I mean bishop Van Bommel who is responsible for the removal of the statue). There is a small paragraph in L’Emancipation published on 4th August 1844 dedicated to this topic.</p>

<p>“Joseph Geefs has sent his <strong>admirable creation</strong> of the Fallen Angel. We have already admired it at the Brussels exhibition. Guillaume Geefs had shown it to us with just and fraternal pride (…). And <strong>today</strong>, we are told that King William II is <strong>taking it away from Belgium</strong> to one of his palaces. <strong>Liège does not want it.</strong> That devil is <strong>too naked</strong> and especially <strong>too sublime</strong>; he has the <strong>flaw of resembling the one in Milton’s work.</strong>”</p>

<p>Let me explain the basis of Milton’s work. The devil from Milton’s poem Paradise lost was seen as an anti-hero, and the church didn’t want that to happen to <strong>their</strong> devil as well.</p>

<p>Now someone might ask „Then why was the statue named “genius” if they didn’t want it to be presented in a positive way?“. Well, as I understand it, the <strong>“genius”</strong> that had Geefs in mind was probably Kantian conception of genius, that influenced romanticism in the 19th century. So “Genius” can be seen as <strong>talent</strong>, not intelligence, and talent can be seen as <strong>an original essence of a being – a spirit</strong>. Consequently, the sculpture’s name could be also translated as <strong>“The Spirit of Evil”</strong>.</p>

<p>Moreover, the Liege’s intimate chronicle states that the statue was removed “with the aim (…) of <strong>no longer distracting the beautiful penitents</strong>  who come to St. Paul to listen to the words that descend from the pulpit!”</p>

<p>According to Royal Museum of Fine Arts of Belgium, the statue was quickly removed because it “did not convey <strong>the Christian idea</strong>,” and „drew parishioners to church <strong>for inappropriate reasons</strong>.“ Additionally the statue “illustrates the Romantic era’s fascination with <strong>darkness, the abyss</strong>, and its <strong>rehabilitation of the fallen rebel angel</strong>.”</p>

<h2 id="iii-problematic-appearance-of-the-first-statue">III. Problematic appearance of the first statue</h2>

<p>After the church’s rejection of Joseph’s statue, <strong>Guillaume Geefs</strong>, the older brother, had to create the <strong>new version</strong> of the devil himself. And he indeed delivered an amazing work.</p>

<figure style="float:center;margin:10px 10px;">
  <img src="assets/img/guillaume-geefs-stat.jpg" alt="Caption Text" width="270" height="500" />
  <figcaption style="font-style: italic; font-size: 13px; margin-top: 5px; text-align: center;"> Guillauma Geefs' statue, the second one;<br />Source: Luc Viatour, 2008</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The <strong>second</strong> statue might seem more <strong>problematic</strong> (for that period of time) in the eyes of a modern person, especially because of the <strong>sensual pose</strong> and <strong>masculine body</strong>, but the church <strong>was satisfied</strong> with Guillaume’s work. To understand their decision, we have to look more deeply into the appearance of the <strong>first devil</strong>.</p>

<p>The <strong>first sculpture</strong> was called „too naked“, because the devil was covered only by a thin layer of fabric surrounding his hip area. On top of that Satan’s legs are slightly spread apart. The fabric in combination with the position of the legs is leaving a gap, that is not really showing anything, but can be considered inviting**.</p>

<figure style="float:center;margin:10px 10px">
  <img src="assets/img/joseph-g-stat.jpg" alt="Caption Text" width="270" height="500" />
  <figcaption style="font-style: italic; font-size: 13px; margin-top: 5px; text-align: center;">Joseph Geefs' statue, called "too naked" <br /> Source: Georges Jansoone (JoJan), wiki</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The sculpture’s gaze and pose were also problematic, as described in The Renaissance Chronicle of Art and Literature:
“The fallen angel sits grave and somber, his gaze turned toward the world that <strong>escapes</strong> him and the sovereign power that <strong>abandons</strong> him. A broken crown and a scepter, which his hand vainly tries to hold onto, symbolize his fall, revealed even more in his contracted features full of <strong>fierce expression</strong>. He is <strong>defeated</strong>, but <strong>not yet tamed</strong>, as <strong>rebellion</strong> can be seen in his <strong>calm pose.</strong>” His expression was also labeled as <strong>“serious, dark, even ferocious.”</strong></p>

<figure style="float:center;margin:10px 10px;">
  <img src="assets/img/joseph-geefs-st.jpg" width="400" height="500" />
  <figcaption style="font-style: italic; font-size: 13px; text-align: center; margin-top: 5px;"> Joseph Geefs' Satan statue, also the first Satan statue. <br />Source: Unknown author, the oldest source I've found is <br /> 2016 pinterest post by "Ivan Mezcua"</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>We can assume, that church didn’t want the devil to be seen as a martyr or powerful revolutionist. 
Furthermore <em>The Art journal illustrated catalogue of the International Exhibition</em> for year 1862 says: 
“‘The Angel of Evil,’ by Joseph Geefs, <strong>is a devil sick, and so far a saint</strong>: the sting of Satan is taken out — the demon, gentle and languid, is almost sentimental and romantic, and has none of the muscle by which Michael Angelo would have made a hero sublime.”</p>

<figure style="float:center;margin:10px 10px;">
  <img src="assets/img/joseph-geefs-genie-du-mal.jpg" width="350" height="450" />
  <figcaption style="font-style: italic; font-size: 13px; text-align: center; margin-top: 5px;"> Detail of the Joseph Geefs' Satan statue. <br />Source: Jean-Christophe, 2018</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>According to Francisca Vandepitte, Senior Curator of Modern Art at Royal Museum of Fine Arts of Belgium he just didn’t look like <strong>“traditional gibbous Satan.”</strong></p>

<p>As a result, he appeared too human-like but exceptionally beautiful, almost like another saint. On top of that, there were no horns and the only thing that was suggesting this statue might be a Satan, was a pair of beast-like wings, which actually just enhanced his beauty.  We can see also snake, but it’s not really distinct. And this leads me to question: <strong>If I wouldn’t tell you, that this is the devil, would you truly know who he is?</strong></p>

<p>To be clear, the devil is often portrayed as beautiful. He was <strong>fallen angel</strong>, after all. And this representation usually corresponds with art of deception the devil is known for. But according to church Joseph’s creation was taken too far in the aspect of the divine beauty. The problem laid in the recognition of the fallen angel. It is <strong>not</strong> an ordinary angel, but an evil angel, the devil himself. That’s why Guillame added some changes and details to his devil statue, that eventually replaced Joseph’s sculpture.</p>

<h2 id="iv-why-was-second-statue-accepted">IV. Why was second statue accepted</h2>
<p>Although the first statue contained Christian symbols, for example a snake next to the devil’s feet or the devil holding a little scepter and tiara, it was clearly not enough for the church to accept Joseph’s statue.</p>

<p>On the other hand, Guillaume was aware of the problems that church had with previous statue and added a lot of changes to his version of devil.</p>

<figure style="float:center;margin:10px 10px;">
  <img src="assets/img/guillaume-geefs-2.jpg" width="400" height="600" />
  <figcaption style="font-style: italic; font-size: 13px; text-align: center; margin-top: 5px;">   Guillaume Geefs' statue, that was accepted by the church. <br />   Source: Vassil </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The copy intended for the church is replaced by <strong>“a less tormented copy”</strong>.  The new Satan wears thicker layers of fabric, and therefore, less skin is showing. His knees are now drawn together. The new statue is also more masculine, with highlighted abs thanks to his pose. Therefore, the devil is less sublime and less delicate. “His tense face expresses remorse and despair.”  His long nails, and especially horns protruding from his disheveled hair, serve to dehumanize the figure. He is even chained to a stone by his leg. Guillame also added religious symbols, such as forbidden fruit with bite marks at devil’s feet or a broken scepter with a symbol of the Morning star. So, the statue was “perfectly Catholic except for the telltale tear of repentance it displays.”</p>

<p>Church was <strong>finally pleased</strong> with this new version, and the Guillaume’s devil <strong>remained in the Cathedral</strong>.</p>

<p>There isn’t much modern news about the statue. In 2008, new information from George Rouzeau from the Liège Tourist Office appeared in his article “Spotlight on Liége” that excommunication of the statue is being considered due to <strong>satanists regularly coming to meditate at its feet</strong>. But according to recent Google reviews and the Cathedral’s website, the statue is still part of the pulpit – even in 2024.</p>

<h2 id="v-final-thoughts-satan-statues-and-the-internet">V. Final thoughts: Satan statues and the internet</h2>

<p>I’ve come across online creators and people in online communities who called Joseph’s statue “a sexy devil”. This description can be indeed intriguing for a modern audience, and it definitely was for me. It makes sense, after all the statue was distracting because of its beauty. But I think the main problem that church had <strong>wasn’t about the beauty</strong> of a Satan alone, but about the <strong>absence of statue’s evil nature in the combination with the beauty</strong>. Imagine an incredible statue of a beautiful, sad, almost naked young man and then there is a sermon happening <strong>exactly above this statue</strong>. It seems to me, that they were worried more about the church’s visitors distraction and maybe even society’s reaction.</p>

<p>Then, some media creators said, that Guillaume made <strong>“even sexier Satan”</strong>. This might seem contradictory since the church’s goal was a change, that would be non-distracting to the visitors, but there might be some truth in that statement. On the archived website of University of Liége is stated that Guillaume made changes, so the statue would correspond more with the classic image of Satan, but he also made him look <strong>seductive</strong>. On top of that, “according to art historian Jacques Van Lennep, Geefs’ work may have been inspired by the poem Eloa or the Sister of Angels by Alfred de Vigny”. The poem tells the story of Eloa, a female angel born of Christ’s tears. She falls in love with a stranger at odds with God. Despite being unable to return her feelings properly, he still manages to seduce her and she follows him “down”. Then he reveals himself to be Satan… So, the second statue might be really considered “sexy” or “hot”, since it is probably influenced by the poem that is actually about Satan seducing innocent angel, that regrets her choices. And finally, the church accepted this “seductive” or “even hotter” second statue. That, again, leads me to the thought, that church maybe didn’t have problem with “seductiveness” or “sexyness” from the beginning, they just wanted it to declare the correct message - to convey the danger of the Satan.</p>

<p>Some people online also claimed or assumed, that Guillaume created the statue to look “even sexier” then the previous one <strong>as revenge</strong> for his younger brother’s statue being rejected. But I didn’t find any source of information that would support this. Guillaume created the new statue with changes so the church would be <strong>satisfied</strong>. If the church rejected the first statue due to it <strong>“being too sexy”</strong>, why would they accept even sexier new statue? It wouldn’t really make sense. Furthermore, it again supports the theory that the church’s main issue wasn’t the “sexyness”, after all they accepted the second, quite seductive Satan. Their issue laid probably more in the gentle look and distracting (maybe even non-threatening) beauty of the first Satan.</p>

<p>In conclusion, the first statue’s main problem was probably the beauty combined with a lack of clear “evil cues”.  This could have made the figure seem sympathetic or even downplay the concept of evil (that makes sense if we consider the reference to Milton’s satan). Guillaume’s Satan was accepted, because the statue was more satan-like and designed appropriately.</p>

<h3 id="additional-information">Additional information:</h3>
<ul>
  <li>
    <p>*Wikipedia refers to the first statue as “L’ange du mal”, but older documents refer to it as “Le génie du mal”. The “L’ange du mal” as a name for the first statue likely emerged later as a way to differentiate Joseph Geefs’ statue from Guillaume Geefs’ statue(which was also called “Le génie du mal”).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>**the information about “inviting nature” seemed really interesting, so I wanted to include it, but its source is a commentary on a reddit <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/interestingasfuck/comments/hsnbmu/statue_of_lucifer_in_a_catholic_cathedral_in/">forum</a>, that’s why I took this information with a grain of salt. According to the reddit user Perse_phone, they heard it in their art history class at Uliége by Prof. Duchesne. They said: “(…) the fabric at the groin is tucked in the second statue, but just delicately placed on the tights of the first one, leaving a gap (you can’t see any genitals but the opening was considered “inviting”)”.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>All of the translations (from french language) were made with the help of Google Translate and AI, so there might be some discrepancies. However, the meaning of the text should still convey the main ideas.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Salon - periodical exhibition of works by living artists</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>In case clarification is needed, the “Annuaire” from 1888 states that Guillaume <strong>himself</strong> initially entrusted the creation of the devil statue to his younger brother, Joseph.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>La Belgique monumentale, historique et pittoresque was written by multiple authors. The quality of the book’s copy is not the best, but the part about Liége was  written probably by the belgian art critic Félix Stappaerts</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The <a href="http://www.opac-fabritius.be/fr/F_database.html">online catalog</a> Romanticism in Belgium from Francisca Vandepitte dissapeared from the internet. I saved the most important part of the text, because I wanted to use it in the article:</p>

    <p><em>„This beautifully built, winged Adonis is in no way reminiscent of the traditional gibbous Satan. Shortly after its installation in the cathedral of Liège, this trouble-provoking ephebe was removed on the orders of Bishop Van Bommel. So much unhealthy beauty might be contemporary, but it still clashed head-on with Christian thought and drew parishioners to church for inappropriate reasons. Just as in Milton’s “Paradise Lost”, the fallen angel also embodies in romantic authors like Goethe, Byron, Chateaubriand and Vigny the irresistible power of attraction of danger and darkness, the romantic fascination of the sublime. (According to Francisca Vandepitte, in cat. “Romanticism in Belgium, 2005”, Online catalog of the Royal Museums of Fine Arts of Belgium, Brussels.)</em></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Vandepitte  wrote a book in 2005 named also “Romanticism in Belgium” or “LE ROMANTISME EN BELGIQUE”. You might find similar information in this book, but I can’t confirm it for sure, since, sadly, I don’t have access to it.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Joseph’s devil statue was installed in the cathedral probably in 1844, since in the same year it was still being exbihited in Ghent (Annuaire, 1888). Also the newspapers informed about the decision of removing the Joseph’s statue again in 1844.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="references">References:</h3>
<ul>
  <li>Sculptures. (n.d.). Royal Museums of Fine Arts of Belgium. <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090624003318/http:/www.fine-arts-museum.be/site/EN/frames/F_sculpture.html">Link here.</a></li>
  <li>Moke, H. G. P. et al. (1844). La Belgique monumentale, historique et pittoresque, Tome 1-2, p. 156. Google Books.</li>
  <li>La renaissance chronique des arts et de la littérature, Tome 3-4, p. 116-117. (1840). Google Books. <em>In the text mentioned as The Renaissance Chronicle of Art and Literature.</em></li>
  <li>Revue belge: Publiée par L’Association nationale pour l’encouragement et le développement de la littérature en Belgique. (1842). Google Books.</li>
  <li>Feuilleton de L’Indépendant: Beaux-Arts (7th April 1843). L’Indépendant [KBR BelgicaPress]. <a href="https://www.belgicapress.be">Link here.</a></li>
  <li>Weelden, A. J. Van (1843). Beaux-arts: exposition De La Haye. p. 61. Google Books. <em>In the text mentioned as Fine arts exhibition in The Hague.</em></li>
  <li>Annuaire de L’Académie royale des Sciences, des Lettres et des Beaux-Arts de Belgique. Volume 52, p. 207 (1886). Google Books.</li>
  <li>Varietes. Salon de Gand. (1844, August 4). L’Emancipation, 15(200), p. 3. <a href="https://uurl.kbr.be/1905250">Link here.</a></li>
  <li>Vandepitte F. (2005). Romanticism in Belgium. Online catalog of the Royal Museums of Fine Arts of Belgium, Brussels.</li>
  <li>Edmond Marchal (1887). Étude sur la vie et les oeuvres de Joseph-Germain Geefs. p. 19. Google Books.</li>
  <li>Annuaire de L’Académie royale des Sciences, des Lettres et des Beaux-Arts de Belgique. Volume 54, p. 315-316 (1888). Google Books.</li>
  <li>Le génie du mal. (2003, February 18). Royal Museums of Fine Arts of Belgium. Retrieved September 23, 2010. <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080413172407/http://www.fine-arts-museum.be:80/site/asp/Oeuvre_details.asp?ID=91">Link here.</a></li>
  <li>De Geest, J. (2006). 500 chefs-d’oeuvre de l’art belge. p. 203. Google Books.</li>
  <li>The Art journal illustrated catalogue of the International Exhibition 1862. p. 318 (1863). Internet Archive. <a href="https://archive.org/details/artjournalillust1863lond">Link here.</a></li>
  <li>Geuzaine, S. Y., &amp; Creusen, A. (2003). Liège au XIXe siècle - Guillaume Geefs, Le Génie du Mal. Wikiwix Archive. <a href="https://archive.wikiwix.com/cache/index2.php?url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.wittert.ulg.ac.be%2Fexpo%2F19e%2Falbum%2F165_geefs_genie.html#federation=archive.wikiwix.com&amp;tab=url">Link here.</a></li>
  <li>Van Luijk, R. (2016). Children of Lucifer: the Origins of Modern Religious Satanism. p. 458.Internet Archive. <a href="https://archive.org/details/childrenoflucife00unse/page/458/mode/2up?q=telltale">Link here.</a></li>
  <li>Rouzeau, G. (2001-2008). Spotlight on Liège. Archive.today. <a href="https://archive.ph/20080515044706/http://www.viamichelin.co.uk/viamichelin/gbr/tpl/mag5/art20080315/htm/tour-visit-liege.htm">Link here.</a></li>
  <li>Wikipedia</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="image-sources">Image Sources:</h3>
<ul>
  <li>John Bedell, The back of Joseph Geefs’ statue. <a href="https://benedante.blogspot.com/2014/05/the-geefs-brothers-and-devil-of-liege.html">Link here.</a></li>
  <li>Joseph Geefs’ statue, also called L’ange du mal. Wikipedia. Source: Georges Jansoone (JoJan). <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Le_g%C3%A9nie_du_mal#/media/File:L'ange_du_mal_(Joseph_Geefs)_cropped.jpg">Link here.</a></li>
  <li>Joseph Fussel, La cathédrale Saint-Paul de Liège. Public domain. Wikimedia commons. <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Cathedral_(St._Pauls)_Li%C3%A8ge,_par_Joseph_Fussell.jpg">Link here.</a></li>
  <li>Luc Viatour, Lucifer Liége. 2008. Wikimedia commons. <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Lucifer_Liege_Luc_Viatour_new.jpg">Link here.</a></li>
  <li>Jean-Christophe. 2018. The Geefs’ brothers and the Evil Genius &amp; Angel of Evil. <a href="https://gay-sculpture.blogspot.com/2018/03/the-geefs-brothers-and-evil-genius.html">Link here.</a></li>
  <li>Ivan Mezcua. L’ange du mal - Joseph Geefs, 1842. Pinterest. <a href="https://www.pinterest.es/pin/486248091001235192/?amp_client_id=CLIENT_ID%28_%29&amp;mweb_unauth_id=&amp;amp_url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.pinterest.es%2Famp%2Fpin%2F486248091001235192%2F&amp;amp_expand=true">Link here.</a></li>
  <li>Vassil. Cathédrale Saint-Paul de Liége. 2009. <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Chaire_Cath%C3%A9drale_Li%C3%A8ge_240809_05.jpg">Link here.</a></li>
</ul>

<p>Some of the images are shared under <strong>CC BY-SA 4.0 DEED
Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International</strong> license.</p>]]></content><author><name>Daidarai</name></author><category term="articles" /><category term="articles" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The year is 1837 and the Belgian church just commissioned a devil sculpture for St. Paul’s Cathedral in Liége. The devil statue was meant to be part of an even bigger project — the new pulpit with theme “the Triumph of Religion over the Genius of Evil”. The sculptor Guillaume Geefs was put in charge of designing the pulpit. The creation of the devil sculpture was entrusted to Guillaume’s younger brother – Joseph Geefs. (…) And Joseph created one of the “most disturbing works of the period” – the Genius of Evil.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/geefs-stat.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/geefs-stat.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>