<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
	<channel>
		<title>Daidarai</title>
		<description>having fun and researching some topics</description>
		<link></link>
		<atom:link href="/rss-feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>Brief: The first known representation of rhinophyma</title>
				
					<dc:creator>Daidarai</dc:creator>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;This painting (1490) by Italian artist Domenico Ghirlandaio named An Old Man and his Grandson (Ritratto di vecchio con nipote) is unique, because it features the first known representation of a condition called “rhinophyma”. The deformity on the old man’s nose can be seen in the painting. I found out about this painting thanks to this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=s6gKTy9oyhA&quot;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt;, where is Dr. Lee treating her patient with the rhinophyma and helping him achieve better breathing with her procedure.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				
				<pubDate>Sun, 08 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>http://localhost:4000/ghirlandaio-an-old-man-and-his-grandson</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/ghirlandaio-an-old-man-and-his-grandson</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Brief: Explore The Ghent Altarpiece by Van Eyck</title>
				
					<dc:creator>Daidarai</dc:creator>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;Beautiful piece of art, right?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				
				<pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>http://localhost:4000/ghent-altarpiece</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/ghent-altarpiece</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Brief: Mappa Mundi, the Largest Medieval Map</title>
				
					<dc:creator>Daidarai</dc:creator>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;I came across an online medieval map from 1300. You can explore this map of inhabited part of the world (roughly equivalent to Europe, Asia and North Africa) yourself on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.themappamundi.co.uk/&quot;&gt;its website&lt;/a&gt;. Aside from mythical races (for example Sciapods, race of people with one huge foot, which they used as an umbrella), that are drawn on this map, there are also beasts, legends and biblical stories displayed. Yes, it is not really literal depiction of the world. Especially with that unicorn and other stuff going on there.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				
				<pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>http://localhost:4000/mappamundi</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/mappamundi</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>This Devil Was Too Beautiful: The Satan statues by Geefs&apos; brothers</title>
				
					<dc:creator>Daidarai</dc:creator>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;The year is 1837 and the Belgian church just commissioned a devil sculpture for St. Paul’s Cathedral in Liége. The devil statue was meant to be part of an even bigger project — the new pulpit with theme “the Triumph of Religion over the Genius of Evil”. 
The sculptor Guillaume Geefs was put in charge of designing the pulpit. The creation of the devil sculpture was entrusted to Guillaume’s younger brother – Joseph Geefs. (…) And Joseph created one of the &lt;strong&gt;“most disturbing works of the period”&lt;/strong&gt;  – the Genius of Evil.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				
				<pubDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>http://localhost:4000/the-satan-statue-geefs</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/the-satan-statue-geefs</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
